Guide to the Joan Little collection, 1973-1975 and undated RL.11599
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Joan Little collection
1973-1975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11599
.6 Linear Feet 1 box
This collection documents the case of Joan Little, an African-American woman from Eastern North Carolina who was tried for the capital offense of first-degree murder when she killed a jailer who had sexually assaulted her. She was aquitted of this charge, and her story became a flash point for women's rights, prisoner's rights, and the issue of racism in the criminal justice system. The collection contains of materials used by Southern Poverty Law Center counsel and documentary filmmaker Morris Dees, including exhibits for the defense and official court documents. Also included is original poetry written by Little while incarcerated, print media clippings, and an original screenplay, "Free Joann Little."
Biographical / Historical
Joan Little (b. 1953) is an African-American woman from the small town of Washington in Eastern North Carolina. In 1974, she was charged with breaking and entering and larceny. She was found guilty and sentenced to the Beaufort County jail. In August of 1974, she was raped by a jailer and subsequently killed him. She was tried and found not guilty of first-degree murder. She was returned to jail to serve the rest of her original sentence. She subsequently escaped, was captured, and returned to jail. She was finally realeased in 1979. Her case became a touchstone for the issues of women's rights to defend themselves against rape, prisoner's rights, as well as racism and classism in the criminal justice system.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Joan Little collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2005.
Collection Overview
This collection documents the trial and controversy surrounding the case of Joan Little. It consists of poetry written by Joan Little while incarcerated, including "I Am Somebody", correspondence from Southern Poverty Law Center counsel Morris Dees to Little's Durham, NC defense attorney Jerry Paul, letters of support and publicity for the Joan Little Defense Fund, trial materials prepared by the defense, official court records from the Beaufort County Superior Court, print media clippings, a North Carolina State publication on prison standards, and an unpublished screenplay, "Free Joann Little" by the screenwriter Joel Olansky.
General
Please note that although the authorized form of her name is Joan Little (pronounced Jo Anne), it also frequently appears as either Joann Little or JoAnne Little. She signed her poems Joanne Little. The spellings of the name on items in the collection have been transcribed as they appear.
African American prisoners -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; African-American women -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; North Carolina -- Race relations.; North Carolina -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Prisons and race relations -- North Carolina; Trials (Murder) -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Women prisoners -- North Carolina -- History -- 20th century; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Little, Joan; Dees, Morris; Paul, Jerry
- Collection, 1973-1975 and undated
  - Letters of support and Joann Little Defense Fund, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Writings by Joanne Little, 1974; Originals and photocopies (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Mostly original poetry written on State Department of Corrections letterhead; includes the poem "I Am Somebody"
  - List of witnesses for the defense, [1975]; Photocopies (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exhibits for the defense, [1975]; Photocopies (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Morris Dees correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Witness interviews, 1974-1975; Photocopies (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes notes by Morris Dees
  - Autopsy report, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Beaufort County Superior Court trial documents, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Print media clippings, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Photocopies from both local and national publications
  - North Carolina State publication: Minimum Standards for the Operation of Local Confinement Facilities, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    General
    Morris Dees' copy
  - Free Joann Little by Joel Oliansky, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Unpublished screenplay submitted to the Lynn Pleshette Literary Agency (169 p.)